<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ritaahmadi.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ritaahmadi.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-24T20:17:02+00:00</updated><id>https://ritaahmadi.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Rita Ahmadi</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Collection of Resources for Learning Topological Quantum Computation</title><link href="https://ritaahmadi.github.io/blog/2022/Topological-Quantum-Computing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Collection of Resources for Learning Topological Quantum Computation"/><published>2022-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ritaahmadi.github.io/blog/2022/Topological-Quantum-Computing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ritaahmadi.github.io/blog/2022/Topological-Quantum-Computing/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="a-collection-of-resources-for-learning-topological-quantum-computation">A Collection of Resources for Learning Topological Quantum Computation</h2> <p>Here is a list of resources for learning topological quantum computation from different perspectives and for various backgrounds.</p> <p><strong>History</strong></p> <p>A concise history of the field is tweeted by Maissam Barkeshli on his personal Twitter account, <a href="https://twitter.com/MBarkeshli/status/1280236950906122241?s=20">here</a>.</p> <p><strong>Introductory Materials or General Reviews</strong></p> <ol> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0707.1889"><em>Non-Abelian Anyons and Topological Quantum Computation</em></a> by Chetan Nayak, Steven H. Simon, Ady Stern, Michael Freedman, and Sankar Das Sarma. This is <strong>the</strong> paper that most others cite, but it is difficult to read if you are a beginner. If you have a solid understanding of one of the following approaches, this paper will help you see the bigger picture.</li> <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qj-w6ISQL5Y"><em>Topological Quantum Computing: Plenty of Room in the Middle</em></a>, a talk by Jason Alicea.<br/> A physical overview of topological quantum computation, including a description of state-of-the-art experiments.</li> <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FAiiXp9IoBk"><em>Topological Quantum Computing: Part 1 &amp; 2</em></a>, a talk by Steve Simon.<br/> If you want to learn about the Kauffman bracket or the Kitaev model, watch these! No one gets bored during Steve Simon’s lectures—they’re always interesting!</li> <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sB5AGbk5Z4Y&amp;list=PLgi8knCht2bKn6ZpvSwqbmXSbP4pIjuF2&amp;index=8&amp;t=0s"><em>Topological Quantum Computation: Part 1, 2 &amp; 3</em></a> by Nick Bonesteel.</li> <li>For more talks, check out this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLgi8knCht2bKn6ZpvSwqbmXSbP4pIjuF2">YouTube playlist</a>. It is ordered by level of difficulty based on an undergraduate knowledge of physics and mathematics.</li> </ol> <p><strong>Holistic and Comprehensive View</strong></p> <ol> <li><em>Topological Quantum Matter</em> by Steve Simon.<br/> I recommend starting with this book if you do not have prior knowledge of topological matter and quantum computation. It walks you through complex subjects while building intuition with humor—you won’t even realize when you’ve learned some of the most difficult topics! It also includes numerous exercises. (Don’t panic when you reach the Surgery and Quantum Gravity chapters—keep going!)</li> <li><em>TQC ZOO</em> <a href="https://errorcorrectionzoo.org/">https://errorcorrectionzoo.org/</a></li> </ol> <p><strong>Physical Approach</strong></p> <ol> <li><a href="https://topocondmat.org/"><em>Topological Quantum Matter</em></a>, an online course described as “a joint effort of Delft University of Technology, QuTech, NanoFront, University of Maryland, and Joint Quantum Institute.”</li> <li><em>Introduction to Topological Quantum Matter &amp; Quantum Computation</em> by Jiannis K. Pachos.</li> <li><a href="https://thesis.library.caltech.edu/2447/2/thesis.pdf">Parsa Hassan Bonderson’s thesis</a>.</li> </ol> <p><strong>Axiomatic Approach Without Invoking Category Theory</strong></p> <ol> <li><a href="http://www.theory.caltech.edu/~preskill/ph219/topological.pdf"><em>Lecture Notes for Physics 219: Quantum Computation, Chapter 9</em></a> by John Preskill.</li> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1601.05288.pdf"><em>An Invitation to the Mathematics of Topological Quantum Computation</em></a> by Eric C. Rowell.</li> </ol> <p><strong>Categorical Approach</strong></p> <ol> <li><a href="http://web.math.ucsb.edu/~zhenghwa/data/course/cbms.pdf"><em>Topological Quantum Computation</em></a> by Zhenghan Wang.</li> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1705.06206.pdf"><em>Mathematics of Topological Quantum Computing</em></a> by Eric C. Rowell and Zhenghan Wang.</li> <li>Appendix of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/0506438"><em>Anyons in an Exactly Solved Model and Beyond</em></a> by Alexei Kitaev.<br/> This paper does not explicitly discuss topological quantum computation but provides a comprehensive account of the mathematical structure behind the model. It does not directly use categorical jargon, but knowing a bit of category theory—at least the definition of a monoidal category—helps in recognizing categorical correspondences. This is one of those papers you might want to keep handy!</li> </ol> <p><strong>Open Problems</strong></p> <ol> <li><a href="http://aimpl.org/fusioncat/"><em>Classifying Fusion Categories</em></a>, edited by Scott Morrison and David Penneys.<br/> A list tracking problems in this area.</li> </ol> <p><strong>Topological Quantum Field Theory (Not an Exhaustive List)</strong></p> <ol> <li><a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/frobenius-algebras-and-2d-topological-quantum-field-theories/A6438118DFADFD27175779F1FC0FF7CB"><em>Frobenius Algebras and 2-D Topological Quantum Field Theories</em></a> by Joachim Kock.</li> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/0810.0344.pdf"><em>Undergraduate Lecture Notes in Topological Quantum Field Theory</em></a>.</li> <li><a href="https://bookstore.ams.org/cbms-133/"><em>Lectures on Field Theory and Topology</em></a>.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="resource"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Collection of Resources for Learning Topological Quantum Computation Here is a list of resources for learning topological quantum computation from different perspectives and for various backgrounds.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Story of Transistors</title><link href="https://ritaahmadi.github.io/blog/2022/Story-of-Transistors/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Story of Transistors"/><published>2022-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ritaahmadi.github.io/blog/2022/Story-of-Transistors</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ritaahmadi.github.io/blog/2022/Story-of-Transistors/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-story-of-a-photo-transistor">The Story of a Photo: Transistor</h1> <p>Susan Sontag wrote substantially on photography and its revealing, sometimes even interpreting objectives. On the difference between a painter and a photographer, she said, `` the painter constructs, the photographer discloses’’. So the claim that one of the most productive teams of the 20th century ruptured because of a single photo might be an exaggeration, but it perhaps discloses some truth. John Bardeen, William Shockley, and Walter Brattain were members of the team who invented one of the most revolutionary inventions in human history, i.e. transistors.</p> <p><a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/c2/Bardeen_Shockley_Brattain_1948.JPG">Picture 1: (from left) John Bardeen, William Shockley and Walter Brattain.</a></p> <p>Shockley was the leader of the Solid State Physics group at Bell Labs with an assignment of building a vacuum tube alternative for improving Bell’s telephone system throughout the country. Shockley, who recently came back from the mission of training program for B-29 bomber pilots, proposed using an external electrical field on a semiconductor to affect its conductivity. However, months of attempts at this idea proved unsuccessful until Bardeen suggested using surface states that prevented the field from penetrating the semiconductor. Eventually, Bardeen’s proposal resulted in the successful production of point-contact transistors.</p> <p>The first cracks in this collaboration appeared when Bell Labs’ attorneys concluded that they could not include Shockley’s name on the patent since Shockley was not the first to propose the field-effect idea. Infuriated by this decision, Shockley independently and secretly worked on the idea of using junctions instead of point contact. This effort ended in the invention of bipolar junction transistors. Receiving recognition and publicity after Comstock Prize in Physics, Shockley’s name was often solely associated with transistors in the media. Annoyed by the media coverage, Bardeen left Bell Labs for academia, and Brattain moved to another group. Shockley later left Bell Labs and established the first cornerstones of today’s Silicon Valley.</p> <p>Perhaps, the next photo they took together was at the Nobel prize ceremony in 1956 when they were jointly awarded the Nobel prize in physics; a ceremony which happened again for Bardeen in 1972. The triplet recreated Picture 1 in 1972, called ``Return to Result’’. It is held under Granger licence.</p> <p><a href="https://static.stacker.com/s3fs-public/styles/slide_desktop/s3/2020-11/croppedGettyImages613469674I9A6jpg.jpeg">Picture 2: (from left 1st) Walter Brattain, (5th) John Bardeen, (7th) William Shockley.</a></p> <p>The invention of the transistor shifted the culture radically, from community gatherings in wealthy neighbours’ houses for watching a movie to the autonomy of tiny devices in school kids’ pockets. Transistors, moreover, shifted the culture, process, and function of photography. It provided a better understanding of semiconductor physics which contributed to the invention of CCD in Bell Labs. In 1975, Kodak built the first digital still camera(DSLR) using a Fairchild 100×100 pixel CCD.</p> <p>Transistors and their grandchildren, the modern-day-ICs, also brought about today’s smartphones. Nowadays, the selling point of smartphones is their cameras: advanced, portable, and equipped with AI assistant corrections. The availability of cameras has further substantially transformed the public discourse from words to photos. To conclude with another Sontag’s quote, “[…] Mallarmé said that everything in the world exists in order to end in a book. Today everything exists to end in a photograph.”</p> <h2 id="references">References:</h2> <ol> <li>Riordan, M., &amp; Hoddeson, L. (1997). The Moses of Silicon Valley. Physics Today, 50(12), 42-47.</li> <li>Sontag, S. (2001). On photography (Vol. 48). Macmillan.</li> <li>Wikipedia entry on Transistor</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="resource"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Story of a Photo: Transistor]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interesting Quantum Papers</title><link href="https://ritaahmadi.github.io/blog/2021/Interesting-Quantum-Papers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interesting Quantum Papers"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ritaahmadi.github.io/blog/2021/Interesting-Quantum-Papers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ritaahmadi.github.io/blog/2021/Interesting-Quantum-Papers/"><![CDATA[<ol> <li><strong>Unified dynamics for microscopic and macroscopic systems</strong>(Collapse Theory) https://journals.aps.org/prd/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevD.34.470</li> <li><strong>The Oxford Questions on the foundations of quantum physics</strong> https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/pdf/10.1098/rspa.2013.0299</li> <li><strong>Google Device Database</strong> https://quantumai.google/hardware/datasheet/weber.pdf</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Unified dynamics for microscopic and macroscopic systems(Collapse Theory) https://journals.aps.org/prd/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevD.34.470 The Oxford Questions on the foundations of quantum physics https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/pdf/10.1098/rspa.2013.0299 Google Device Database https://quantumai.google/hardware/datasheet/weber.pdf]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Poems</title><link href="https://ritaahmadi.github.io/blog/2019/A-Poem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Poems"/><published>2019-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ritaahmadi.github.io/blog/2019/A-Poem</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ritaahmadi.github.io/blog/2019/A-Poem/"><![CDATA[<p>Before ChatGPT becomes extremely poetic, I used to write poems, even some of them received prizes!!! Now I try to understand which ML models make better poems!</p> <p><a href="https://www.seh.ox.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/Teddy-Hall-Magazine-2020-pages-compressed-for-website.pdf">A Poem Called Bukhara</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Before ChatGPT becomes extremely poetic, I used to write poems, even some of them received prizes!!! Now I try to understand which ML models make better poems!]]></summary></entry></feed>